[Music]
at least from my point of view as i'm
speaking
um i'm thinking about this as the
the unfolding meta crisis so the the
rolling out of the virus and our
response to the virus is an aspect of
the metacrisis
but there's the second order and third
order effects many of which are going to
be as impactful
and so it's the whole thing so when i
think about that
um and we spoke about this earlier in
the context of new york city
that there is effectively at the very
top is choice between
do we respond to this by breaking uh
into
to by balkanizing into us versus them or
do we respond to this by coming together
into we right and in many ways that's
the most important piece um
and you talked about the fact that you
have a sense that the uk has a
both an instinct and a capability of
of coming back together into a we
under times of crisis well and you think
they will yeah
i think i'd like to recap that because
we're talking about stuff we
we discussed we started recording but
yeah my sense and i've always had this
sense is that the uk
there is such a thing as a coherence of
the national conversation in the uk
it's sort of held it's held in various
places held in the centrality of the
of the the fact that the media and the
politicians all went to the same
universities it's held in the centrality
of london
it's held in the bbc it's held there's
there's just a kind of coherence to the
national conversation
um and it's obviously on a deeper level
held within sort of very british values
of
um which have been sort of tested
recently but sort of fair play
and all of those kind of traditional
british values
and i do get a sense of coherence that i
don't get from the american conversation
which is really
the american talent is like dialectic
it's
and that's what drives america forward
but it's also it's also a
centripetal is that central centrifugal
one of the two
people centripetal force that pulls
apart
um so that's my sense of what a
america or no i think it's centrifugal i
think i think you're right the
centrifuge pulls things apart yeah the
centrifuge
um so yes and i think we can actually
get
even a starker relief so in the past 48
hours
serbia kind of the archetype of
balkanization
the president said europe it turns out
europe was just talk
like we cannot get any help from europe
they're not sending us support they're
not sending us mass nothing as
ventilators
europe everybody in europe is sort of
pulling back and taking care of
themselves and letting everybody else
ride
we must rely on our brothers in china
okay so the european experiment so if
you look at like
uh the us is a highly heterogeneous
country particularly in comparison to
any other nation it's by far the most
heterogeneous
but europe is as itself is also
heterogeneous as a unit
and doesn't really have any tradition of
being able to come together into a
synthesis
so one it's a very reasonable
expectation that the european experiment
is now deeply deeply in trouble because
the people are beginning to realize the
only way for them to take care of
themselves is to take care of themselves
um with the possible exception that we
might see germany do something extremely
powerful
and ramp up something that can actually
support europe as a whole um
that would be by the way a very
interesting turnabout like the the final
like okay it turns out in when
the chips that we go with the hits
the fan it's not world war one it's not
world war ii
the germans are also able to be the guys
who pull things together that'd be a
good a good result
um and then okay so that's europe and
and this notion of like okay wow serbia
really showing us what balkanization
really means like what's the opposite of
a collective conversation and then we
have the the american side
and the american side we have this uh
frankly it's very fractal
right so i mentioned that new york is
just going super critical right the
number of cases are
are steeply accelerating probably
because of detection not because of
spread but the felt sense of that is
hitting
but my my intuition actually feels
confident
my intuition feels confident because
there's those characteristics of new
york city in particular
that you've got a bunch of people who at
the end of the day are very practical
and very hard-edged i think they like to
get done like the formality of
conversation new york is funny
you like within 30 seconds if you're not
talking about something that is
worth my time get the out of here
um
but two they actually have a sense of we
right to be a new yorker is a thing
and you can look across the line and see
a guy who's you know
two generations ago his his his
ethnicity was
didn't speak the language was somewhere
completely out and you two generations
ago we're also
but you're both new yorkers and
you can help each other and then third
they have the cultural memory of
september 11th
so they actually have a live sense of oh
okay we remember what crisis feels like
can we remember what it feels like to
come together as a as a people
so the ability of new york city to
respond is at least in potential very
high
but in many ways for america this is how
it goes as you say it's a
question of do we have
the capacity the willingness and the
capacity to take
all of the gradient all the difference
that's embedded in who we are
and bring that back together into a
higher synthesis right it's not a
this is the state and this kind of
cycles like this it is a spiral
right if you kind of look at our case
history
in 1776 yes
80 years later in 1860 no
80 years later in 1940 yes
80 years later in 2020 question mark
right so we're going to find out and
i mean we were saying just before as
well that
i certainly my sense i think you agree
is that this is going to play out very
differently in different countries
because it's going to test
it's going to basically stress test the
society it's going to stress test the
culture it's going to stress test
the um the memetic complex that we call
national identity it's like this set of
characteristics
and i think it's going to play out very
differently in different countries
depending on that
yeah it's funny like you can even say
that it's a bit of a uh how would you
how would you name it it's like um
i guess the best metaphor i can use is
that notion of like a sonar ping
um because you get this this
the shape of almost like the the
interior of a culture
so compare like like we have to be very
very precise let's compare
singapore to china so if you look at the
china's response
and by the way i'm not going to run the
model of the chinese are actually acting
in a
strategic machiavellian man i'm just
going to run in the model that's kind of
like they're acting as they
they themselves would like to be best
perceived so in the chinese response you
have something like
corruption bureaucracy
political maneuvering leading to a very
bungled response where whistleblowers
were shut down
and and city leaders who knew stuff were
directed not to share things
for too long and by the way let's be
very careful
uh under that model
the world has this because of that right
it got big enough in china that it did
spread globally
but then right once once a pivot point
happened the chinese response kicked
into
the other side which showed up as a
really
amazingly remarkably harsh level
of shutdown like people being like
police just going door to door to giant
apartment buildings and literally just
welding them shut right no voluntary
quarantine
no that in china they just lock
your ass into the apartment building and
good luck to you
and people on the streets just being
grabbed and thrown into cars
like the level of capacity there was
high now
net net it seems like it worked right so
that we can look at the chinese model
and say huh
on the one hand we get a sense of what
that approach looks like you know
a very uh you know high corruption and
high bureaucratic and
and cover your ass and difference
followed by super
harsh top down almost ruthless levels of
of
of protection from the top and it
results in
um x level of impact
look at singapore by contrast
you know the singapore right now is
still the probably the most well-oiled
machine on the planet and they
simultaneously reacted almost instantly
as soon as there was a real threat
everything shut down it did not shut
down with significant ruthlessness
but it did shut down with enormous
completeness
and kind of still is like they've done
it they're probably the best job on the
planet
uh and there's something about the
nature of singapore that has that
they're still a very hardwired but
somewhat smooth
kind of well integrated command and
control infrastructure
look at korea you look at japan i think
we're going to go globally so you get
this very interesting
perspective on the one hand of getting
like a how is it how did i say this like
a
open kimono insight into the true nature
of how a culture really operates in
response to crisis
um and a you know
for whether we like it or not a uh uh
a revelation of the reality of that
culture's current capacity
[Music]
and let's let's sort of recap the
we you mentioned the meta crisis so
maybe let's
and we've featured you talking about it
on the channel before but
obviously now it just just has a kind of
ramped up relevance and i think maybe
more people are starting to realize
exactly what it was that
uh was trying to be talked about do you
want to kind of outline where you think
we are in the meta crisis and what you
even mean by that
in this context of just the people that
most people are focused on right now
sure um so the the concept is is to
point out
i guess a couple of things i'll start
at the top and work down so at the top
is the
is the recognition that
we live in a nested set of many
different systems that are all part of a
larger system and are connected in very
complex ways
and this sort of has always been the
case but quite often
we don't have to pay that much attention
so
the um kind of the classic case in point
right now
is that we don't usually think about a
a viral crisis like a truly health
crisis
as also being an economic crisis
a bunch of people getting sick is a
thing that the doctors and the cdc are
supposed to worry about
and we're kind of worried about whether
or not and how many people get sick and
how bad that is
we think about our own personal health
and the people think we love
we don't imagine that the people at the
federal reserve board should be watching
that crisis very closely because those
aren't the kind of same kind of thing
they should be watching interest rates
and real estate prices and stuff like
that
and yet of course they're connected and
there's a transition
where the called the subsystem the part
of our
larger system that kind of takes health
very seriously and looks at it very
closely
it gets overwhelmed and the consequences
the impacts
cause just from an economic perspective
the externalities of that subsystem
start throwing externalities out into
other subsystems
which now need to be paid attention to
and if you're not paying attention to
them you get blindsided
you just get whacked in the back of the
head because you weren't looking at that
you were looking here
and that just slammed you
so at the meta level the point
is that and this is the the the
hypothesis that about operating under
for now for about 15 years
is that this has been going on for a
long time in fact
it just hasn't been acute it's been
chronic so
the 2008 financial crisis in america as
a
financial crisis um
had the systemic infection where it
spread from the united states to europe
and then spread from europe to china and
then kind of
cascaded around we're like oh all right
we forgot each
country's economy and each country's
financial system is connected to all the
rest through a global financial system
we have to be able to think about that
as a whole system
which as far as i can tell we very
distinctly fail that and we're actually
worse at managing it as a whole system
now than we were in 2008.
um but equally
uh we see that there's there was a
spillover effect that the way that we
responded to
in in the states to the 2008 to 2010
crisis and the way that
you in europe they responded to the 2010
to 2015 crisis
spilled over into the social and
political day we got we got the tea
party and eventually we got trump
from that i think it's very important
for people to recognize that the causal
structure
that leads to trump begins well it
doesn't begin to has a big push
in the financial system in 2008 and the
causal structure that leads to brexit
begins
or at least has a very strong causal
connection
to the european debt crisis and how that
was responded to
the way the banks were bailed out and
the technocrats
really did push
harm to people and protect uh proximal
institutions created a big deep sense of
don't trust those guys
and that cascaded out so that's been
going on
and um kind of to put a line in the
middle
the the theory is that
that there's a uh a driver in our
culture a global culture
at least in the dominant sense of like
neoliberal globalism
that has a strong bias in the direction
of optimization for
efficiency of a specific set of metrics
so what that does is that that basic
sort of fundamental
deep driver gives you that metric
at a high level right so you can get gdp
up
but at the cost of fragility it pulls
you you get one metric optimized at the
cost of other metrics
other things that matter being down
regulated or at least made
vulnerable and so you become fragile
and you don't necessarily notice
fragility until something
heavy or hard or fast hits the system
okay so you have to combine these two
one is that we actually have a whole
bunch of different systems that are
actually deeply interconnected but in
ways that we
oftentimes don't watch and in some cases
aren't even aware of
and then two we've been going through
the process for seven
decades of trying to optimize these
subsystems
which makes the systems and the meta
system
increasingly fragile okay so now we have
today
what i would say is that what we're
experiencing right now was baked in this
was going to happen
it was just waiting for the right
event right the right perturbation the
right magnitude of effect to hit
a subsystem with enough speed and
or impact that it began the process of
creating cascade effects to hit other
subsystems and pushing beyond their
fragility levels so that they began to
break and throw externalities into
still more subsystems right so it's a
cascade failure across
different literally different modal
systems so it's one thing for like the
finance system the u.s to hit the
finance system in the uk
because at least they're both financed
and we can kind of like think about them
in the same way
it's a little bit harder when the
finance system hits the economic system
because
sometimes we can't even distinguish
between the two and recognize they're
very different
but it's a real deal when the finance
system say hits the health system
and we really have a hard time even
thinking about how they relate
so so all of that is precursors and
saying okay right now where we are is we
are witnessing
in real time that happening that that
fragility
being revealed in uh very complex
relationships
in sub-systems so let's be very concrete
um the number of beds
per capita makes a big difference to how
your country
will weather the viral storm one of the
weak
points is what's called medical system
overwhelm and it's funny how like we can
watch the culture evolve
a month ago that phrase medical system
overwhelm
didn't really exist more and more people
began to look around and say oh
that's the thing that matters
and then the name spreads we now have a
concept medical sister overwhelmed which
is to say
the uk just recently sort of published a
big paper that talks about this in a big
way
if i've got a medical system that is
designed to be able to handle
you know 10 icu cases
per thousand people per month
and i suddenly jumped to 11.
um it's kind of like this phase
transition where i've got a a pint glass
that's what you guys drink right pints
yeah and um you know filling it up with
beer
there's a period of time where it's just
sort of more and more full
no real like whatever it's all it's all
kind of the same dynamic it's half full
it's three quarters full there's also
variations of full once it actually hits
full i go through a phase transition
where it's spilling beer all over the
floor
and that's a different kind of thing
right now instead of just sort of
closing the tap and handing it to
somebody i have to think about oh
how do i scramble do i clean it up
you know externalities are spilled into
the into the pub
so if i've got a medical system that's
designed to handle 10 icu beds
per thousand people but then i have a
an epidemic that suddenly moves me to
11.
that eleventh bed isn't just plus one
now i actually have a completely
different dynamic because i don't have
the capacity to give them the medical
care that they need like where are they
they're not in an icu bed where are they
are they like thrown into a tent outside
or they just left
dying on the floor like what what's
happening there they get to the 12th
the 13th the 14th to 15th and we've seen
this very practically in
mortality statistics you know in places
where the medical system is not
overwhelmed
the mortality statistics tend to be
vectoring into
less than one percent in places where
the medical system
is overwhelmed they tend to be vectoring
towards greater than five percent that's
a big switch
and that's just a very and that's like
not necessarily even the thing that
matters it's a nice
sort of visceral hard point you see that
okay so the the number of beds per
thousand people around the world varies
quite widely
i believe korea was somewhere around 10
or higher
whereas the u.s is is around two well
why is that
well the reason for that is because the
american medical system has been
optimizing for efficiency
for a long time and so up until now two
has been kind of
good enough we've never run into a
situation where we needed more than two
and then holding an extra icu bed when
you don't need it
has an extra cost basis which decreases
the bottom line so this is like
a long-term impact of the financial
system and by the way also the
governance
system conspiring to lead to fragility
at the level of the medical system
which we didn't really have to deal with
until we had to deal with it which is
right now
so that's a one piece it's very concrete
in which we're running into
well that's a lot i just said a whole
bunch of words i don't know how much of
it is uh
coherent or how much of it lands but
maybe uh what's next
yeah i mean we could use that point to
expand from there really because
i mean that that seems to me to be the
most constructive
large frame to use which is that we've
got a system that optimizes for
for efficiency therefore takes all of
the slack out of the system
by definition you then don't have much
resilience in any of the systems because
any extra capacity would be
would be surplus to requirements
therefore inefficient so you
you create by definition like fragile
systems all over the place
yeah and by the way so we're gonna go
deep do you mind going deep here let's
go deep
um these are super fundamental concepts
this is the kind of stuff that i should
have been putting in my own channel
all right evolution you know we i use
evolution like brett often to make sense
of things in this case it's very
important
so the sabertooth tiger
is optimized for efficiency
it's very fragile to changes in its
niche
it goes extinct so what happens is this
if i have a niche if i have a uh an
environment
that stays relatively static
for a long enough period of time what
ends up happening is that the way to be
successful
is to find a niche and then to optimize
for efficiency in that niche right
because
there's no point in holding things that
don't aren't valuable because it's been
long enough
that change ain't going to come and so
the saber-toothed tiger that sort of
doesn't have the long teeth and has the
shorter teeth is less effective in the
context of a particular environment than
the one that has the long teeth
so it keeps selecting for longer and
longer teeth bigger body mass whatever
the characteristics are that make it
the peak predator now okay
and so niches that say static for a long
enough period of time and by long enough
what i mean is literally in relationship
to the evolutionary cycle of the
underlying organisms
so for safer tooth tigers they have a
reproductive rate and a mutation rate so
if you have like
a million years of the same environment
you're going to get
very optimized organisms
and in evolutionary theory it's very
clear we know that
very optimized organisms are also very
fragile organisms which means that
a relatively small change in the
environment
leads to a catastrophic effect on their
genome which is to say extinction and so
if you'd say like
for the for the for the hedgehog when
the environment changes by
ten percent the hedgehog actually only
has a
two percent decrease in reproductive
effectiveness because it's actually a
relatively generalized creature
whereas the saber-toothed tiger with a
ten percent in
change in the niche it goes to zero it
just completely goes away because it's
kind of sitting on top this extremely
rarefied very particular thing
and of course the actual inverse is true
where the environment is changing
relatively
commonly you get these creatures that
are super generalized
which is more that's how humans resulted
right we happened to emerge in an
environment where
we kept going through situations where
the polar the ice ages kept coming and
going and coming and going and we're
kind of going from a place where we had
lush forests and then suddenly like
grasslands with
trees in between and then deserts and
then back in and you know
only those tool kits that were able to
maintain the sort of efficiency of
generality were able to survive at all
and then each bottleneck kicked that off
to the next stage
okay and remind my by the way i've got
one more major conceptual toolkit that
needs to be dropped in but i'll finish
this one
so one of the things that happened in in
the world
is more or less after world war ii and
particularly after the fall of the uh
of communism we had two dynamics that
hooked together uh one was an
entrainment meaning that that what would
had otherwise been a whole bunch of
different niches that were behaving
differently
like we talked about earlier france
being france and germany being germany
in the uk in the uk
suddenly started gluing together into
one meta niche so a company that
peugeot which perhaps was effective as
an organism inside france
suddenly was not as effective in an
organism called global trade
you know daimler benz and toyota were
just
more competitive and so in the context
of the global this new sort of
global niche local
organisms suddenly started evaporating
they just couldn't compete we started
getting this
entrainment of one giant beach
and the second thing we had was this
thing called the great moderation
where the intentional
deliberate and effective use of
regulatory capacity
was able to maintain a stasis of niche
for a long enough time relative to the
reproductive mutations
rate of of human cultural
and social organisms that we became
fragile
and i mean that not only at the level of
systems they also mean that at the level
of
institutions so
for example somewhere in the late 70s
we should have actually had a big
handoff
of socio-technical responsibility
from the 50s era
mentality and organizational structure
and in fact
individuals to a rising wave
literally in a different biological
generation but also a different economic
and
uh technological generation of
techniques
and the the wave of digital capacity
and peer-to-peer communication that
we're trying to figure out now
should actually have gone through a
normal childhood in the 70s
and by the 90s should have that in fact
have been handed off
in a what's that called a peaceful
transition of power capacity
which would have been ended by the way
sort of the banking system would have
more or less gone away
because we don't actually need banks
that concept is a very
mid-century concept the banks that we
actually currently understand
i'm hoping that's your mom it's perfect
no it's rafi's wife margret it's perfect
right this is this is uh yesterday i was
having a conversation with john verbaki
and my daughter came inside of my lap
like this inner penetration of the
of the real like our real lives this
sort of notion of the artificiality of
the office is going away and we're all
sort of in our homes which
is part of the cultural revolution we're
going through um
so we got instead was this this sort of
continuous doubling down on the
optimization for a artificially
constrained
niche for example the banking system the
financial system
which became saber-toothed tigers
everywhere if you didn't
dispense with resilience inside your
banking system and double down on
derivatives trading you were not as
effective in competing for
alpha and beta as the guy next to you
and so you got it selected against
and everybody became safer chief tigers
and so that's very important
um and let me
re say that again to make sure it really
lands um
that that i actually described two
different dynamics that happened
one was an artificially constrained
longer than it could and should have
been duration of a niche
like the sabretooth tiger's niche which
generated an
enormous amount of selective
evolution into highly optimized
structures
and by the way optimized for that
artificially constrained niche and
it's very important to say artificially
constrained because the
the forces of change were building up
it's like you're talking about with
france
right france the french language like
this notion of we're going to use a
human institution the academy to hold
the language from evolving
and hold it and hold it and hold it but
the forces of change are building up
technology is changing culture is
changing the times are changing and so
it ends up happening that environment is
it doesn't elegantly move it actually
just has to shatter
and you have kind of a breaking event
and then change happens all like
willy-nilly
and then some new state hits and that's
kind of what happened right we had a
whole bunch of governance institutions
that had the capacity and
the intent to manage the globe hey we
don't want
bad things to ever happen again to
anyone
and they were effectively able to kind
of hold change from happening
and they held it and held it and held it
what they did is they pushed change out
from a from a sort of an elegant smooth
movement to this
building up on the outside of the dam
inside the dam
we had artificial sameness which caused
these
saber-toothed tigers to evolve in all of
our niches our academic system
our medical system our governance system
our scientific academies you know eric
weinstein's been hammering
the same why in the world have our
journalistic and our academic
institutions
been increasingly steered by guys who
were born in the 1940s and 50s what why
isn't there any fresh blood coming in
literally just a human level and this is
why this is why
so what happens is we put ourselves in a
situation where when change
comes it's going to come hard suddenly
the damn
bursts like the levees bursting in
katrina in new orleans
and it bursts into an environment where
all the resilience has been
sucked out of the system so it breaks
and breaks and breaks and breaks and
breaks and breaks
um okay so that was a big conceptual
payload
and if anybody landed it i think you're
gonna get a whole lot of orientation
about why we're where we are
where we are and what's likely to
continue to happen and by the way
if this particular event doesn't break
through
all the rip stops and tear things apart
it's just a matter of time
unless we figure out how to reverse the
polarity and begin to actually
evolve again and rebuild resilient
anti-fragile capacities
yeah i'd like to in a moment talk about
the the stress and the crisis of sort of
making sense of it
uh and how how kind of the media and the
collective intelligence have shown up
but just before we do that i'd love to
recap you said something
i saw a talk you gave a couple of days
ago where you talked about
addiction and the similarities between
denial that have been showing up i'd
love i'd love to hear that piece for
for our audience oh yeah okay well
that's
i mean that's another conceptual model
and it's important and it's a big one
that fits in here as well
and it really resonated with me because
i've been dealing with
like having a close personal experience
of that dynamic of
of denial of denial of reality and then
kind of
that moment of kind of realization so
yeah i'd love to hear it yeah
all right so so we have like let's call
it a baseline cycle and unfortunately i
don't i don't know the name so maybe you
can find it and put it in a little
subtext i've forgotten the name but it's
the basic
cycle of you know denial and acceptance
and bargaining and all that stuff
um and this seems to be just a natural
that's a kubler-ross uh stages of grief
yeah yeah that's right that's exactly
right so there we go uh so the
cooperative stages of grief seems to be
a part of just
psychology and frankly there's probably
really good reasons for it it's been
selected for over long periods of time
and lots of different content
and think of that as like the natural
thing so no matter what when you run
into something that's going to hit you
with a
big shift in change you will go through
that
so don't fight it swim swim with it
so when you're feeling um uh
really depressed by the realization that
things
are much worse than you thought in some
sense if you can be metacognitively
aware of the fact that you're in the
right place
and just kind of allow yourself to
process that in the way it needs to be
processed so you can get into the other
side of acceptance
as smoothly as possible not as quick you
can't make it go faster than you can
then you're then you're doing as well as
you can
and i want to put a particular note i've
noticed in myself at least
four of these cycles the last one was
two days ago at three a.m
um so something's going on right now
with this the rate of change and the
magnitude of change and the quality of
changes such that
acceptance which is to say to begin to
step into building an adaptive response
to what
is actually finds itself yet again
overwhelmed by a change of what is that
is big enough in magnitude to require
that you actually go through a whole new
cycle
so that's kind of like an unfortunately
powerful part of what's happened
but then we actually have a different
dynamic and this is the dynamic of
addiction
which has to do mostly with denial
so this is a breakdown of our sense
making and choice making system
where reality hits us
and i think it's actually not it's this
this is koopa ross system but a
particular subset of what happens it's a
uh
a reciprocal closing of their reiki as
rebecca describes it
so reality hits us um
and we kind of have a choice we can
either
deal with the this cycle deal with the
unpleasantness of this cycle and the
necessity of actually changing our
behavior
or we can ourselves
right and we have that choice and
if we happen to have in some sense the
privilege the benefit
of being able to ourselves and
not have reality really kick us in the
teeth
it's all too easy to ourselves
and if the magnitude of change
that we have to go through in the
context of reality feels
uncomfortable enough right so we get
this kind of separation this is why by
the way
uh addiction can really really hammer
the wealthy
because money allows you to buy not
changing
a lot easier you don't hit rock bottom
as painfully
which is kind of an odd thing like
oftentimes people who don't have
resources
get you know it gets really bad because
they do hit rock bottom
but the amount of sort of what gets
pulled with them in duration in life
may in fact be shorter cycle we hit rock
bottom in years as opposed to in decades
but in any event as a culture this is
particularly the case so in the west
the max the massive plenitude we've been
able to produce over the last 50 years
70 years
has given us the ability to sort of kick
the can down the road
to go into bullshitting ourselves
and avoiding the uncomfortable reality
of the necessity of changing
what are in fact rather significant
pieces of our behavior and our
infrastructure our
institutions and by the way stepping
into a lot of uncertainty
change requires actually stepping away
from certainty into uncertainty and that
by itself is uncomfortable
and of course if you do that if you
yourself
reality well sometimes reality just goes
away sometimes it actually works out
sometimes the thing that you were trying
to avoid thinking about actually does go
away and you can
yeah i got away with it which by the way
reinforces the behavior but generally
speaking it doesn't
generally speaking reality is reality it
doesn't really care how much you
yourself in fact generally
speaking if you
push it yourself you do make matters
worse
so you know the next day reality comes
knocking at the door and says hey it's
time to change
and something just went wrong again
you're faced with a choice but now
you're kind of deeper in
because the magnitude of your
the the delusional story
that you begin telling yourself and the
the self the self denial
and uh the narratives that you
constructed to enable your
um have a bigger control over where you
are and you have to actually go
through the field you have to feel all
the discomfort that you've been delaying
at once so instead of being discomfort
of one now it's just comfort of three
so you have a choice you go deeper into
the rabbit hole and yourself
even further or do you suck it up and go
through the even bigger bag that you've
changed you have to go through
well generally speaking people will
often choose the first path
and again if you can get away with it if
you can
throw more it's just used like
the financial system is a very
concrete example in 2008 reality hit us
and said
you guys have been really this
up for a long time the global financial
system is
not functional it's hyper fragile it's
optimized for efficiency it's making bad
choices bad resource allocation
functions
got to change this in a big way big
bank's got to go
probably even centralized banks is a
mechanism they've gotta go this whole
structure
and our global collective intelligence
governance system said oh that sounds
really painful
nope you know i'd rather do i'd like to
take a double shot of heroin and
amphetamines can we get a big shot of
perimeter amphetamines
well yes we can okay good let's do that
instead
um and of course over a period of time i
was like well that amphetamines wasn't
enough we need a lot more
which is like uh putting a load of money
quantitative easing
just basically printing money right yeah
let's cut interest rates a quarter point
well i didn't work okay let's cut it
half a point that didn't work let's go
to zero interest rates well that's not
working anymore let's go to negative
interest rates
that's that kind of that cycle and the
point of that stage is that each one of
those decision points was a decision
point where you could decide either to
yourself
more or suck it up and actually go
through the change necessary
to get to actual sobriety and so at the
level of the financial system
like uh the reality had percolated
through the crisis had kind of come
enough to an end that by the time that
we were sitting around
2014 2015 2016 um
and our capacity for producing
stimulants was strong enough
that we went through a a felt sense of
another high but it wasn't a real thing
right the underlying damage was pretty
heavy it's a little bit like you can
imagine that you were running a race
and uh you like fell and sprained your
ankle really badly
um but you just decided to wrap it up
with some tape and then
inject yourself with the combination of
painkillers and stimulants
and just went back running on the on the
ankle well
if you're under if you're when you're
under the influence of the painkillers
and the stimulants and the the wrap
is kind of good enough you might
actually be running pretty well
but you're doing damage to the ankle and
when the stimulants and pain codes wear
off
you're now even worse than you were
before so that's that's what's happening
right now in the financial system
the magnitude of what's being done right
now in the u.s and this is going to
cascade globally of course
is like a whole step up from everything
that happened in the period between 2008
and 2012. like it's like two or three
times
x already we're only four or five days
in
um which is to say that we're just
continuing to choose to
ourselves
the addict is continuing to choose to
update the
delusional story whatever you do don't
pay attention to what's real
and doubling down on the the
the stimulant the thing that allows the
system to continue to operate as if
reality isn't what it is uh and you know
eventually
as every addict knows you hit rock
bottom
um and you always have a choice when you
hit rock bottom you have a moment of
clarity
and the moment of clarity you can
finally choose to just take in to get
into complete acceptance
and by the way oftentimes the i believe
the story is to uh
submit to a higher power to surrender
and begin to say okay i really don't
know how to deal with this i need to
actually begin learning from the
beginning
again and realize i got to take my lumps
actually have to grow through
the change that has to happen to get to
sobriety and ultimately the health
um or you can go right back down to the
denial cycle until ultimately death
right and i think that's again that's a
really good conceptual model as we've
done we've kind of been moving back and
forth between the
individual human biological example and
the financial example
um and by the way if you'd like you can
transpose this to the
political side for example um
but what would it look like for like if
this is denial what would it actually
look like
to to face reality and what would the
changes
need to be
i mean okay just adjust the list rather
than maybe
kind of yeah yeah but this is something
that i've been looking at for now
again about 15 years so it's actually
not that in some sense it's not that
mysterious i've already already
laid out most of it yeah the first is to
accept you got a problem let's do aaa
like the aaa guys have cut it
kind of wired first except you've got a
problem like stop
denying that you've got a problem second
begin the process of coming into
awareness and relationship with the
reality of the problem like begin the
process of actually stepping into
reality so in this case for example
i would propose it would be quite
helpful to have a
collective conscious acceptance of the
reality of the medic crisis that i've
been talking about
that the thing in front of us the acute
crisis
is a symptom of a much larger chronic
crisis that has been ongoing for a long
period of time
and to to reach a level of acceptance of
the magnitude of change and in some
sense at least the qualities of change
that need to occur
for example if i'm a baby boomer
who has been holding on to the reigns of
power
of particular institutional structures
for a long time
i think it's time to acknowledge the
generational transfer
is an actual necessity i think it's time
to acknowledge that the reality is is
that
i don't really know what to do and
that's okay
it's not my job to know what to do there
are other people who are younger than me
that have grown up in completely
different environments that have better
instincts and better learnings about the
reality that we currently live in
it's their job to know what to do
now i may actually have a deeper
connection to why if i've lived life
well and full and thoroughly that i
actually have developed embodied wisdom
and i can start trying to
present why and this notion of we
who we might be like the deep tradition
the deep tradition is still carried in
my body and the way that young people
can't have
but the specific strategy and response
that we ought to be engaging in
okay boomer is a archetypal and
practical sign of the reality of that
case
you're out of the loop you don't
really understand what's going on in
reality
and yet you're still clutching on to the
reigns of power
with uh what's my cold dead hands that's
just one example i don't mean to harsh
on that that's just a very specific
example
two if you happen to be in charge of a
very large
powerful institution it's time to
recognize that institution probably
needs to die
sorry big too big to fail banks
the right response is you actually need
to go away
that's just the reality and i understand
this is not an easy thing to do
it will be challenging but doing it
consciously intentionally and
deliberately
rather than with our hand forced by
crisis coming from 15 different
directions
and by the way now geopolitical movement
of other people realizing
that weakness in crisis is an
opportunity to take advantage of things
it's just a better idea so if we had
back in 2008
recognized that the too big to fail the
response to too big to fail banks was no
longer too big to fail banks in the
world
we would be massively better off now so
that's another example and by the way
education want to pick another poison
the global education system particularly
the american education system
the right response right now is to
recognize that it's just a mess
top to bottom and this is not a matter
of trying to tinker around the edges
with
different testing methodologies it
really is a time to say okay
wow i've actually got every american
school child is no longer in school and
possibly for the next six months
now is the time to really think about
hitting a reboot on the whole thing and
can we rapidly
pull together an entirely different
approach to education and here's the
thing again
if you're running the education system
you don't know what the to do
you've been focused on trying to figure
out how to maintain the patient for
so long that you maybe have real amazing
expertise in maintaining the patient
but by definition that means you haven't
been spending a lot of time in yourself
working on the way that you think about
things and how to respond to
new possibilities but there are other
people who have been
i think sam obergia actually put it i
think very precisely
the only appropriate response right now
is hand the keys over to people who are
both smart
and brave there are people who are smart
but are coward cowardly that's not gonna
help
the people who are brave but not smart
that's not gonna help either although
there's gonna be some interesting
consequences but there are people who
are both smart and brave and and many of
them are out there like again if you
kind of let's rewind all the way back to
the beginning of our conversation
there were many people in social media
who called this thing
their sense making frameworks their
methodologies of of kind of
estimating risk and sorting through the
noise
worked they saw what was happening and
they actually were able to propose
appropriate responses in a time frame
where it would have been a very easy
thing to deal with
that we don't have to sort of lurch from
crisis to crisis
but the powers that be right now have
neither the capacity or the willingness
to give them the keys right so it's
it's a big deal right and this has
already happened though this has
happened in the past
in uh the period of world war one and
world war ii
the old guard of the of the victorian
era
went through a process of demoralization
in
in the in world war one a process of
trying to hold on to control using old
techniques in the period between the
wars
that eventually was completely
destabilized in a meta crisis
which eventually led to world war ii
where finally
new blood new vital capacity that it was
appropriate to the
to the 20th century right people who
weren't 19th century thinkers
were then given the keys and they were
able to rebuild an entire global system
that got us all the way to where we are
right now
the first three quarters of which was
amazing
that just has to happen again right the
old guard at the the mid-century
has to hand the keys over to a new guard
who have embodied capacity to actually
be aware of
where we are things like digital natives
if you're not a digital native you need
to stop trying to control things
if you're a digital native you've got to
get your together and start using
those tools
and upgrade your uh your bravery which
is to say
my language your sovereignty which is a
lot of stuff you guys have been working
on is being able to communicate
all right how do i do that how do i not
be all right so i did this from the top
let's do it from the bottom which is i
think a place that you guys
really do a lot of so let's take the
people who
are well positioned are much maligned
millennials um
one of the good consequences of our
horrific education system is they don't
actually know much about
lots of stuff um which is actually not
bad because
in some sense it means they're not held
back by by stuff and they can learn new
stuff
they can maybe try to rapidly bring in
the right kinds of stuff but here's
what's holding back millennials
they haven't built sovereignty they
haven't taken upon themselves the
responsibility
that they actually need to have to step
into
running the world this extended
adolescence
the fact that 35 year olds are
ultimately where ben franklin was when
he was nine
is uh the nature of that problem
it means cognitive responsibility you
can't just drop into some prefab
ideology that allows you to kind of
dunk on people on the internet that's
not reality that's adolescent
you need to grow up what is it wake up
grow up clean up
step up some something like that show up
i think show up that's what needs to
happen it needs to happen on mats in
particular for the people kind of like
35 and below and the people by the way
55 and below in the people 65 and below
85 and below i think right now is sort
of buttoned down and and survive
but different variations on that theme
but stepping into sovereignty
psychological emotional spiritual
um cognitive
rapidly adopting and building adaptive
capacities in the context of what is
happening and what is real
is the nature of the game at every
single point and this is more
true than is usually the case
because the nature of what is real now
is that the answer to the question
is in fact decentralized or distributed
collective intelligence
the solution to world war ii was the
blue church
we've talked about this many times it
was a meritocratic
vertically integrated hierarchical
system that used
mass as its primary modality mass
broadcast mass production that was the
topological solution that was available
in the mid century mid 20th century
that's not the answer now the answer now
is a continuous connected
network that uses spontaneous
coordination the ability to create
bespoke solutions at the edge
think about like micro targeting and the
danger of micro targeting the point of
view of propaganda
but now think about macro targeting and
its opportunity at the level of
empowerment
our system right now has the capacity or
at least could have the capacity under
wartime
parameters in months like three four
five months
of using our collective wisdom
perception intelligence to generate
a signal to literally every human being
on the planet of precisely what they
need to be most fully empowered to
provide
to make the best choices for themselves
and provide the best
capacity into the world so imagine right
now if you had some kind of dashboard
where the world was conspiring
to provide you with the information you
needed and the relationships and
resources you needed
to then simultaneously make you better
at what you do
and to allow you to give your best
capacity back into the world
that's just by the way that's what this
thing looks like when it gets to
maturity that's what it looks like and
i'm not kidding and we have the capacity
to get there
in a very short period of time
[Music]
we probably won't but at some point i
sure hope we do
because that's the only kind of thing
that can actually respond to the
magnitude velocity and complexity of
what is happening
and will continue to unfold in a series
of phase transitions
until we actually respond to it unless
we don't in which case
it collapses completely
yeah you mentioned i mean you've talked
about collective intelligence in this
context before decentralized collective
intelligence
and i wanted to just to quickly touch uh
we're kind of coming to the end i just
want to quickly touch on sense making in
this context
and how i remember i spoke to you and
you said that
the collective intelligence sense making
around
the virus was like two to three times
uh or at least sort of two orders of
magnitude higher than what was going on
within the mainstream media
yeah we've put out and i think we'll put
them out again underneath the
in the show notes for this like all of
these amazing
shared resources and uh public documents
that are linking together all of this
kind of new information and
the latest data and then what to do
about lockdown et cetera et cetera et
cetera so
like that we are seeing it start to
happen
yep but you fear that it's not going to
be fast enough
i fear that it's not going to be fast
enough
so let's give a nice like another
concrete example um
doctors and medical scientists
right now are being hampered by the
institutional silos
that they are in they're
really really wanting to have some kind
of open
shared communications platform where the
things that are being discovered at the
edge like
the etiology of particular patient
characteristics and the
high the newest findings of like genetic
testing
on on the virus um and uh what
whatever the science and the practice um
globally what's going on in india what's
going on in china what's going on in
singapore what's going on in new york
what's going on in yorkshire
um they want and need a capacity to
completely boundary-less like
the bureaucracy national health
service let your doctors run
cdc the best thing the cdc could do
right now
would be to just let go and let the
people at the edge begin the process of
spontaneous coordinating
they're getting in the way like nobody's
business and the tools are getting in
the way so with the policies and the
procedures and the tools
and to a lesser extent because the
psychology can change quite rapidly
under these conditions
the psychology is getting in the way
because they're an artificial bottleneck
working on a broadcast model that
insists on
everything going through their system
and it's just not they're not capable
of of doing it yeah so remember i've
said this like 15 times over the past
five or six years publicly the blue
church like which is
this particular construct of everything
at the edge having to go
up to the top to a set of decision
makers to evaluate what's happening
and then make a set of decisions and
then propagate that set of decisions
back down
that's that approach at its best
couldn't handle the velocity and
complexity of what we're dealing with
right now
and it is very very far from being at
its best
so now let's take that story and let's
make it very concrete
testing swabs cdc
so here's the deal
we have a testing methodology we have a
test test kits
there are in fact a lot of test kits
sitting in hospitals all over the
country
the test kit involves a swab
that swab can pick up lots of things by
the way including covet
it is entirely physically possible for
the doctor the hospital at the edge
to do a test on that swab and verify
whether or not the patient being tested
has or does not have
the disease they aren't doing that
because the regulation requires them
to send that swab up to the cdc to be
tested
and then the data comes back from the
cdc
by the way in true american style what
they could do
is take two swabs so you've got two
nostrils
send one up to the cdc and test the own
the one in their lab and basically tell
the cdc to themselves
minimum minimum compliance to stupid
rules is kind of a good idea right now
in any event that's a good example right
it's just
institutional incapacity why is the cdc
holding this obligation which can't work
because it doesn't have the resources to
handle the flux of input
and the time delay between you're just
shipping something out here and coming
back
is a big deal it's a real problem why
well i mean you could sort of go put on
your tinfoil hat and start talking about
conspiracies
and maybe but more likely
a combination of senescent and fragile
institutional structures
and the feedback loop of um
fear-based responses and the inability
to move through the uh
the denial and learning cycles that's
the most likely explanation
something you pointed out that was
really interesting that struck me um
that the difference in responses between
different
character types and you mentioned kind
of people on the right
of the political spectrum like
republicans who
generally you would expect to be very
disease phobic they score much highly on
um kind of questions of purity and
we're actually responding very
differently and we're kind of
really in denial for a lot longer than
people on the other side and there was
all this narrative about what it's just
a
it's just a democrat um fear-mongering
it's just attacking trump and then we
had this
this sort of catastrophic level of kind
of denial followed by panic
um and then a complete change of that
narrative like you had fox news go from
this is all kind of made up to this is
not made up and trump is dealing with it
and he's a war president in the in a
matter of
kind of hours almost what do you make of
that
yeah so i was quite confused by that and
i think you may we even had
conversations
on it in social media and somebody gave
me uh
the insight that i think is right which
is we're kind of dealing with a
a bit of a topsy-turvy unraveling of
context
so two things happening simultaneously
one is
at least in the us and i think maybe
broadly
among political conservatives among the
people who are in the right
there is a a well-deserved conventional
wisdom
that the mainstream media is not our
friend so a
a visceral response an intuitive
response that if the mainstream media is
conveying something particularly
convincing with a high degree of urgency
that it's probably wrong it's probably
false
and it's yet another example of them
trying to kind of whip up
um unconscious response for agendas that
are not
in my best interest as a person from the
which is to mean to say that they had
built over a long period of time a
detection system
and they gave them a false negative
paint you know
the boy who cried wolf more or less
cried wolf 100 times
i've stopped listening to you oh
there's a wolf back in the vibe
the second thing and kind of in the
middle is if you actually do
have at a dispositional level a
high orientation towards purity
and towards strong closed clean borders
the gap that you have to get over
between this isn't a problem to it is a
problem is actually quite
high if you have to actually go through
a whole bunch of oh
this is actually a really big
problem because your your disposition
will perceive this as actually being a
much bigger issue
so on the one hand you have this denial
vector which is
they cry wolf we know these guys
are manipulative lives who don't have
the best interest in mind
i have heuristic of not listening to
demand oh if i do listen to them
then this is gonna really be scary and
bad and i actually feel quite powerless
because i don't have any way of
responding to the violation of our
boundaries and purity at this level
so this kind of reinforces a delusionary
denial mindset
that was perfectly actually and there's
also when you hit when you hit when you
hit the moment of clarity
when something hits and usually by the
way it goes at the level of
leaders like it's like when tucker
carlson who has a lot of people like
he's he doesn't fit this
criteria we trust tucker on the right
trucker's like oh okay
if he says something he's definitely not
the kind of guy he's actually several
times over the past couple of years
spoken truth to power from the point of
view of the right in a way that feels
like it's even more honest
so when he says no it's a big deal
pay attention then suddenly it's like
i can't go with the boy who cries wolf
he's not the boy who cries wolf
now i got to go through the denial thing
and figure out how to adjust the reality
of it
but then you kind of this whole
construct flips and then you settle into
the base
which is conservatives respond as a oh
this is a violation of purity and
integrity and now
we it's a crisis like so it moves from
denial to crisis pretty quickly
if you're landing in kind of that
natural disposition
yeah that feels right and the other part
is just the motivated reasoning of
like on both on all sides of the
political spectrum you just see people
intuit what the end game would be if
this was true
therefore it can't be true for example
the end game being there's going to be a
big hit to the economy and that will
harm
trump's re-election chances therefore it
cannot be true
if you think about it it's a fascinating
psychological mechanism because it means
that subconsciously
we are able to play that out without
being conscious of it
and then refuse to play it out
consciously because we've realized where
it would go if we actually did it
yep happens all the time right when you
uh you know you you walk somebody
through
you know you're sitting in a city that
has a you know
a plant like a chemical plant
and you're talking about the negative
impacts of the chemical plants
operations on the the local river
you keep it very tactical yeah we've got
the river and the water supply and the
fish and the frogs and the chemicals
that are being output in the river
having these consequences
and smart people are paying attention
they're nodding yep yep yep you kind of
show you do you see these curves and how
that works
yep get it and also there's a point
where suddenly the conclusion is
i'm going to lose my job and there's a
retcon of the entire
and suddenly things that they had agreed
to explicitly
15 minutes before they are now disputing
with the absolute level of uh
with vigor so yeah that's for sure
that's a real thing that's a
it's a big deal right and i think it's
actually kind of important to recognize
that that's the case
and recognize that that whole cycle is
part of the cycle like it's not
good enough to have done this
cognitively you kind of have to absorb
the implications in a full body sense if
you have to actually process
the whole implication the whole
consequence and you have to do it by the
way not just here but all the way
through
i just had to have your response
and not have gotten stuck in any level
of denial i go through the whole process
and not had a little
piece of you say ah i don't want to deal
with that i'll go into denial now
really you know integrate the whole
thing then you're fully in acceptance
then you can go through it yeah there's
an interesting story that really fits
with this that i heard earlier today
a friend of mine called dougald hein
talked about how he had a meeting with
the government during the
swine flu crisis in the uk i think it
was swine flu or it might have been foot
and mouth i can't i think it might have
been foot and mouth actually
yeah yeah the meeting with the
government advisor and outlined
what it meant there was a big outbreak
in in mexico and he kind of explained
what it
and then midway through the meeting
after about an hour he realized he
wasn't arguing what with with someone
who was trying to decide what the right
thing was to do
it was what is the most that i can sell
to the media
and that that for me feels like a very
deep
um a very deep systemic floor and it's
what i'm paying
particular attention to at the moment in
the uk like the uk strategy
seems almost entirely based on that like
if we signal panic now having signaled
that we're kind of quite easy and
we're talking about herd immunity if we
signal panic now
it will invalidate like what will the
media think of us and it's like
that that to me feels like a very deep
if you you outline
china as being the opposite of that it's
like i don't give a because public
opinion is
is completely irrelevant and russia is
the same
but that seems to be a deep systemic
flaw with
representative democracy that they don't
feel they can level with us
uh about reality and therefore there's a
kind of untruth built into the system
and and then there's a there's also a
responsibility on the media there
because
the media often will overplay things and
so you get these sort of multiple
failure conditions where no one feels
they can be honest because they'll freak
people out
and then then everyone's just making
decisions based on what will be thought
of them
and the rather than the the decisions in
themselves
it's like artificiality does that work
is that sort of you've mentioned
baudrillard's idea of simulation
yeah is that the process that he talked
about
um well he doesn't talk about the
reverse definitely talk about that
yeah and i think that's right that's a
very good frame i mean it's a little bit
uh
philosophically intense to use as a a a
frame but yeah
so but i think we can actually make it
reasonably again concrete
and actually throughout the notion of
wartime president i think that's a good
distinction
there's just a difference between peace
time and wartime
um and one of the problems of course
this with peace time is that this notion
of simulation
can work and in many cases actually not
necessarily the worst
thing to do um there's like a
an intuition and a practicality of
managing the crisis
how do i keep people from panicking how
do i stay
in control it's funny like as i'm saying
this at the level of like political
sociology think about it from the level
of individual psychology as well
how do i stay in control how do i make
sure that
that
the things that i want to happen happen
the way i want them to happen
and of course what happens is like if
you're boris johnson or the trump
administration or
you know the opposite number on the
other side of the aisle or any you know
agency head in any regulatory
environment where i've got this kind of
agenda where i'm thinking okay i've got
a lot of different things i need to take
care of i got to take care of my pension
i've got to take care of this deal i've
got over here i've got to make sure i
look good i've got to think about my
all these different characteristics of
what i'm trying to manage
and the method that i'm trying to use
is this notion of managing other
people's perceptions
that's the key managing other people's
perceptions is the tool
that is selected for in a in a peacetime
environment
in an environment where um broderiad
simulation
level two or level three or level four
are in place where reality can be
avoided i don't have the consequences
that come back to me at the level of
society at the level of human
humans are significantly more meaningful
than the reality that comes back to me
through
nature through reality so it is worth
mentioning what
not outlining completely but just that
baudrillard level two three and four are
just increasing levelers
levels of artificiality in the system or
dis
or deceit and dishonesty it's called
like almost like
distance from nature and an embeddedness
of increasingly kind of things that are
dominated by the about
by how humans do things so you might
imagine like um
i'm somebody who lives out in the woods
by myself
and my pipe breaks that's kind of level
zero
i am hands on directly with reality
physical reality
and the pipe doesn't give him what
story i tell myself i either fixed it or
i didn't
so it's very simple okay layer two
um i i call a plumber
and so both my capacity for agency
of actually solving the problem and in
some sense my capacity perception
of knowing whether the problem was
solved adequately is mediated by another
human being
so narrative enters into it right i have
to find some social mechanism in this
case money by the way as a variation on
narrative
i have to find some social mechanism of
getting this
other human to do a thing and that's
the simulation level one right narrative
actually now becomes more important for
my success
than direct relationship with nature
okay let's go to level level two um i
don't even know plumber
i wouldn't even know what to tell the
plumber i have to call the supervisor
the super of the building i have yet
another person
um and the super by the way i have to
convince the super
that it's a good idea i've got this
whole sort of back and forth
set of political dynamics and layers
where um
the super is busy and the super's got
different values and maybe this isn't
isn't an issue for the super to deal
with
maybe it's a you know it's a
squeaky faucet it's not it's not a leak
hey i need the plumber to come fix my i
need somebody to come fix my faucet
and i have to go through this political
mechanism mechanization we have to do
like
performative signaling and political
maneuvering i got to figure out how to
like
manage the perceptions of this agent who
themselves then has to manage the
perceptions of an agent so i'm like two
degrees away from me
okay let's go to layer three um
now we're in the in the fact that we're
in a layer where
storytelling is the medium so like i'm a
journalist
so what i'm doing is i'm actually the
i'm not dealing with now
a a problem in physical reality i'm
dealing with a problem in
narrative reality what are the stories
that people are telling
it is the rare journalist who goes all
the way to the to the pipe
and says ah yep leak i've leveled up in
the capacity to determine yeah that's a
leak that's a real problem
the journalist is interviewing other
people they're talking to ideally
they're talking to the plumber they're
probably talking to the super
they may be talking to the poor bastard
at the top and the journalist is not in
the business
of solving the problem at the level of
the ground the journalists in the
business of creating a narrative
that goes percolates out through
multiple layers of mirror
let's go to layer four now finally i've
got the politician
and the politician is communicating not
to people not to supers
not to plumbers and definitely not to
pipes but to the media
right and of course what happens when
you're in that level of depth
the the niche what it means to be
successful
is increasing in the direction of
actually selecting for which is
to say selecting for
highly salient the kinds of things that
our sense-making system
human perception thinks is important and
true but not necessarily at all
relevant right can i tell a good story
is the story
compelling you know is it a would it
sell in hollywood that kind of thing
and it's perception management 101 so
i'm actually kind of in real time trying
to figure out
what's the movie and when i'm a
political operator instead of level four
and when the whole culture is now kind
of sitting in level four because we
don't none of us are connected to
to the pipe um now we're in bed we are
level four
and um sorry we went a long way down
that path but
i wanted to use that as a metaphor but
the point is um
wartime peacetime so
in the peacetime army and by the way
peacetime civilization the peacetime
country this movement towards this top
of the stack or deeper into the
beautiful environment
is it can be done you can kind of uh
you could be more successful you will be
more successful in virtue signaling
than being virtuous if i could if other
people believe i'm a hero
is much more important than whether i am
a hero and by the way
if i am a hero if i blow the whistle the
whistleblower
i might just be thrown in jail so
bizarrely enough
actual virtue is oftentimes punished and
virtue signaling
is oftentimes rewarded and this is what
creates corruption
in the choice making system war
in this metaphor and more practically in
many cases is when reality comes
rushing back to hit you in the face it's
that moment of clarity and level of the
simulation
um you know the the general who is
very very good at spinning things to
make himself look good but the end of
the day is incompetent
and i don't know if you know the history
of world war ii but manages the battle
of kasserine pass where the american
the american army for the very first
time met the german army in north africa
and got
um well a whole bunch of dead
people and burned down tanks
is kind of hard to spin when people care
they're paying close attention like oh
like no you up dude you must
be a shitty general
and this could actually that that you
kind of do that forward projection oh
this could actually end up with
like the germans winning the war this
would be a bad thing like you can
actually
i don't like i don't like the
consequences of having shitty generals
right now
i need to stop having shitty generals oh
how do i get rid of shitty generals
and so you begin to relearn the process
of at the end of the day
you actually have to know whether or not
the pipe's going to burst and try to fix
it
and so kind of these cycles of at a
meta-systemic level of going through a
process of kind of going into the
simulation
and separating virtue and virtue
signaling and then coming back from the
simulation and rapidly learning the
virtue of signaling is oftentimes
the best virtue signals are almost
certainly the least virtuous people
because they've been optimizing for
simulation
and the most virtuous people oftentimes
are awkward virtue signalers
they look shitty
but they're actually really good and so
reorienting your capacity to make that
discernment
and then making your choice go you know
what people who are actually engaging in
personally damaging heroic activities
have to be supported and rewarded
otherwise we're all going to go down
with the ship
that's that evolution yeah this has been
a fantastic conversation
i just like to round it off with you
mentioned war
wartime and i i used to be a uh producer
for channel four news i was in
uh libya the i mean the most intense
environment that i was in was in misrata
uh when it was sealed off and we
we were there basically the only way in
was by boat gaddafi's army was attacking
it
uh tim hetherington and chris hondros
had just been killed so it was kind of
very heated they had kind of bombs
dropping on the city
i didn't i don't know if i enjoyed it i
i was in kind of combat zone a couple of
times after that
and i and i have to say the feeling
the feeling that it that i was feeling
in london
this last this last week of sort of ram
ratcheting up of tension and attention
and kind of more and more
increased super awareness of kind of is
that person coughing
and like just just this kind of also
increased awareness of just the tension
of
of everyone around me and then your kind
of nervous system starts to kind of
speed up and you're uh felt very very
similar
like it felt like let's let's define war
i think i think i think what you're
saying is actually very very right now
is that
actually it also it's this sort of sense
of something coming in through your paws
almost
right this this sense of like intensity
and
that there's enough what i'm going to do
as well just i want to lodge this i did
an amazing interview with a guy who made
a film
he's an israeli film director he made a
film about the lebanon war that he
experienced
and he was a he was a tank gunner in
that war and he made a film
where you are stuck inside the tank for
the whole two hours of the film to try
and convey what it
felt like and he talked beautifully and
lyrically about
how war gets into every pore of your
body and how it just
becomes this all-encompassing thing i'll
put a link in the show notes to this
interview because it's amazing he talked
about it beautifully sorry you you go
for it
oh great yeah so so what i want to do is
i want to say okay let's use that but
then
let's use it use it rightly and we do we
don't want to overly map
war so things like tanks
that's a that's kind of a good example
uh world war ii vietnam uh libya these
are good examples of war but it's not
the whole of war war is when
choices are being made in very high
levels of
uncertainty where the consequences will
be
very real and oftentimes very
rapid that's war that's what war is
where is that situation and
so in some sense we're fighting we find
ourselves in a wartime posture often
it's like the exact inverse of addiction
the exact inverse of denial
like your choices matter right now like
if you didn't
buy food two or three weeks ago
you're showing up at grocery stores
going what just happened
and so your choice back then was
uncertain
should i be buying food too now why that
makes no sense it's no good ideas you're
uncertain
and it matters now you may actually find
that you don't have enough food
which you might be feeling a little bit
concerned about right now and rapidly
two weeks you found out whether or not
your choice was a good one that's war
and in our environment as the magnitude
of that goes up right so
not having enough you know ho hos is not
that much of a problem
and being shot at is a big problem and
being shot at by malevolent actors who
are good at what they do is even bigger
problem
um but we're facing a situation where
the
the uncertainty is growing
the magnitude of the consequences is
growing
and the speed of the choices is
accelerating
that's why people are having a visceral
sense of oh wait particularly anybody
who's actually been in combat
yeah okay this feels like that because
it is that it's just happening in a way
that we're not familiar with
we're not being nobody's gonna drop a
nuke
on manhattan but the net net
consequences of the entire systemic
uh envelope unfolding may be very
similar and
at the edge like at the edge of what
could happen here there may be a
situation where for example
you know the streets of rome right now
are more or less empty
the collapse of rome back in uh i think
800 or so
do you know that story like this is
actually the kind of thing that people
really need to get
sorry this is way too there's so much
going on here i hope this isn't an
overload i hate overwhelming people but
so in like 500 a.d something like that
maybe 400 400 a.d the population of the
city of
rome ancient rome was 1.2 million people
more or less
300 years later without the use of
nuclear weapons right it's just the use
of
systemic collapse across a wide variety
of different uh fronts
the population had gone down to like ten
thousand people
three years of magnitude from 1.2
million to 10 000 people
over what is effectively a very short
period of time and then it stayed there
until 1939.
that's what systemic collapse looks like
now i'm not saying that necessarily that
will happen
here but the point is if if you realize
that topologically
this idea of uncertainty
velocity and magnitude
by magnitude i mean the fact that
reality really happens the choices
really have consequences
is what war feels like that's the way of
thinking about the nature of
why we are now in a wartime situation
there you go
cool thank you jordan that was really uh
fantastic conversation so
stay safe and um look forward to
catching up again soon
bye bye rebel wisdom is a new
sense-making platform bringing together
the most rebellious and inspiring
thinkers from around the world
if you're enjoying our content then you
can help us make more by becoming a
subscriber
which will give you access to a load of
exclusive films
also you can then join our group zoom
calls to discuss the ideas in the films
and you can send us ideas for questions
for upcoming interviews
we're also looking for talented people
to help us out with editing graphics
music that kind of thing
and if you're a regular viewer you'll
know we talk a lot about the value of
embodying or actually living out the
ideas that we talk about
so that's why we run regular events in
london check out the links on the
website for more
and hope to see you soon